[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
what are we going to do today I thought
I would uh perhaps teach you a little
bit about
cosmology and the extension well just a
tiny bit about the extension from
General from special relativity to
general relativity just a little bit and
then how general relativity is applied
in
cosmology what real SpaceTime is like as
opposed to uh the flat
featuress boring SpaceTime of of special
relativity the SpaceTime of general
relativity is active it's curved it
responds to
things and
uh allows all kinds of wonderful things
to happen such as as the evolution of
the universe the big bang and so forth
so I thought we would just discuss that
a little bit spend
um couple of hours seeing if we can
encapsulate and
summarize basic very very basic uh
cosmology if there are no objections to
that and there are no questions about
previous things I'll begin yeah quick I
hope question U last time we derived
maximal equations I want to be sure
understand the constraints the condition
all we assumed was that there is some
there are some attributes of electric
electric magnetic fields that are in is
that corre pretty much yep well no this
this there's much that we assumed uh yes
we assumed there was some electric and
magnetic fields we assumed that the
equations for electric and magnetic
fields are Loren and variant of course
and that had a that went a long way to
deriving the structure of Maxwell's
equations but we also assumed that the
equations were
linear in other words every single term
in the equations involves at most one
power of the electric and magnetic
fields uh that there were no terms with
electric field times derivative of the
magnetic field and so forth that would
be said uh we would say that that means
that uh that the field theory is
linear I'll tell you what that means in
a moment more
specifically well it means what I said
that the that the fields come in only to
the first Power we also assumed that uh
that Maxwell's equations had did not
have higher derivatives in them that
there were no terms in the Maxwell's
equations with 16th derivative of the
electric field or
something
um those were
assumptions but with those assumptions
Loren and variant
and the assumption that the electric and
magnetic field fit into a single entity
that uh that transforms coherently is
enough to prove Maxwell's equations the
statement that
um
that a theory is
linear what that means is let's suppose
it's a theory for some field or some
coordinate or some degree of Freedom
let's just call it fi it could be a
field it could just be the position of a
harmonic oscillator any quantity which
does something interesting you have some
equations for
it and there are solutions and the
solutions will be of the form f of x and
t well if it's a field it'll be a five
of x and
t which is some definite function I
don't know what to call it except let's
call it a of X and P that's a
solution if the equations for a theory
are
linear then among other things that
means that if you multiply a solution by
any number it's also a solution so if
you have a
wave you can multiply that Wave by 125
or anything else and that will just uh
magnify it or amplify it make the
waveform higher and deeper without
changing its shape other than to stretch
it and to make it uh Stronger that
that's still a
solution so doubling the amplitude of a
wave tripling the amplitude of a wave or
multiplying it by a very small constant
any number is also a solution of the
equations that's one statement the more
interesting statement that is that if
you have two solutions a ofx and another
solution B of x and
t then the sum of the two of them is
also a
solution so what that means is that if
you have two different waveforms for
example let's say a waveform of looks
like this another one which oh I don't
know has a higher frequency smaller
wavelength looks like this if you add
them up you'll get a wave which looks
like a little hard to draw but uh let's
draw it
one wave superimposed on the other just
add them and that's also a solution so
you can add waves one implication of
that for example is if you have a wave
moving along it's coming in from the
left and another one coming in from the
right uh if you didn't have the left
wave the right wave would simply move to
the the right wave would move to the
left and eventually just move off the
left wave would move to the right and
also just move
off the sum of the solutions after a
long time would just be two waves moving
past each other linear equations have
that feature that waves which are
propagating let's say toward each other
will just pass through each other
without scattering without uh getting
stuck without anything happen they're
completely transparent to each other
they don't affect each other because the
sum of the solutions is still a
solution so
uh that's the character that's one of
the features of Maxwell's equations
linearity as I said what that says is
that two electromagnetic waves will just
pass through each other without doing
anything at
all now electromagnetic waves can talk
to each other so to speak they can
interact with each other but they
interact with each other by virtue
of interacting with electric
charges and electric charge which
happens to be present maybe a whole
bunch of electric
charges the whole bunch of electric
charges uh will be excited and vibrated
and tend to have forces on them because
of the electromagnetic fields moving
through and so a field moving through a
bunch of electric charges will start
them
oscillating and create new wav waves
those New Waves which were not present
in the absence of the charges cannot be
thought of is in any sense the sum of
the original two waves is just newly
created waves and so there are nonlinear
effects in
electrodynamics but only because
electromagnetic waves can affect charges
and charges can affect electromagnetic
waves and the net effect can sometimes
be for one electric uh one electric wave
to affect another electric
wave that's the classical theory of uh
of electromagnetism no direct effect of
one electromagnetic wave on another now
you could
imagine um let's write in a linear let's
write down some linear equation any a
harmonic
oscillator the harmonic oscillator the
equation is DC X by dt^ 2 this is the
acceleration times the mass
is equal to the force which is minus
some spring constant time x suppose I
have a solution of this equation and now
I take another solution of the equation
I'll just write it down again instead of
calling it I'll call this X1 and
X1 another solution dx2 by DT ^2 = -
kx2 these correspond to two different
solutions of the same equation if I add
the two equations
I just get that M * the second
derivative of X1 + X2 is just equal to-
K * X1 + X2 so you see directly from the
form of the equation that the sum of two
solutions is another solution but
suppose I change the equation suppose I
put here another term let's call it a p
time X1
SAR plus something else Q oh sorry plus
uh P X2 ^ 2 these are
both Solutions of the same equation but
the equation is now nonlinear nonlinear
means it has quadratic things in the
fields x s if you add these
equations what you'll
get M * DC X1 + X2
by dt^ 2 = minus K * X1 +
X2 but the last term here p is not X1 +
X2
sared it is not X1 I've written it but
it's not true px12 + PX22 is not P * the
sum of X1 and X2 2 so X1 + X2 is not a
solution of the equation when you have
something quadratic there simply just
doesn't solve the original equation even
though X1 and X2
do there's no doubt that you could have
added things to Maxwell's equations
which are nonlinear nonlinear means that
it would contain on the right hand side
of the equations things quadratic in the
electric field things quadratic in the
magnetic field analogs of this here with
which
would which if they existed in maxell's
equations would cause electromagnetic
waves not to pass through each other not
to be transparent to each other but one
electromagnetic wave would affect the
other and cause it to scatter it cause
it to uh to do other things so you asked
me whether you can derive Maxwell's
equations from the principle of
Relativity alone I think that's roughly
what you asked the answer is no no
there's much more
uh in
it some of it coming from experimental
physics such as the fact that
electromagnetic waves do freely pass
through each
other but you add together a few
assumptions linear not too many
derivatives in the equations and that's
enough but no you can't derive uh I
don't know any basic law of physics that
you can derive just from relativity
alone without some input of a physical
um of a uh experimental
type
symmetries constrain theories but they
don't determine them as a rule okay any
other
question good all right so let's uh
let's move on to first of all a little
little little bit about general
relativity very little but then on to
cosmology what real SpaceTime is really
like expanding SpaceTime inflating
SpaceTime
uh which cannot be described by special
theory of relativity it requires a more
General structure called the general
theory all right the special theory of
relativity can be
summarized
by a very simple
idea that there's a
geometry of
SpaceTime and that geometry is
determined by knowing the distance
between every pair of neighboring
SpaceTime
points this is a fact about geometry in
general about ranian geometry in general
that if you know the distance between
every pair of neighboring SpaceTime
points that in principle you can
reconstruct the entire geometry of
space
uh I'll give you an example in a few
minutes but but of a non-trivial
geometry but you represent
then
the small interval between two points by
a coordinate a set of coordinates we can
call them X mu where as usual mu runs
from 0 to three and another point x mu
plus DX mu where this little interval is
called DX mu what's the distance between
those two points the distance between
those two points of course it is
whatever it is it's a what is it it's a
certain SpaceTime interval there but how
do you represent it in terms of the
coordinates of those points in general
relativity we wrote that the distance
between those two points D S2 is equal
to DT ^2 minus d D x^2 - d y^ 2 - dz^2
which we can also write as DX mu DX mu
and another way that we wrote it was
adaa mu
new DX mu DX
new where Ada was just a matrix a very
simple
Matrix oh did we call this too proper
time maybe we call it to now proper
time uh
where Ada was just the Matrix 1 -1 - one
minus one zeros everywhere's else those
are three ways that we wrote the
SpaceTime interval between neighboring
points now uh one statement of the
general theory of of the special theory
of relativity excuse me the special
theory of relativity is that the tal
Square
should be taken to be an invariant of
the geometry in other words all
observers generally they will not agree
on what DX is if we rotate coordinates a
Lorent transform coordinates they'll
disagree about the components of DX but
what they will agree about is the proper
time between the two points so the
proper time is an invariant that's one
uh that's
one initial starting point for sort of
axiomatic description of special theory
of
relativity the second statement which is
not an axiom it's a theorem is that the
Transformations that you can do on x y z
and T which preserve the
form of the
interval are
Transformations if we look at Lorent
Transformations and rotations and so
forth the interval in terms of primed
coordinates has exactly the same form as
the interval in terms of the unprimed
coordinates so that's a statement of
symmetry that the basic proper time can
be
expressed in all lorence frames by the
same basic formula and then the final
statement is that having found what the
symmetry of the interval is having found
out what the symmetry of the what what
family of
coordinates always gives the same answer
here for the interval then the rule is
all Spa all laws of physics are
identical in those different frames of
reference which are related by Lorent
Transformations now of course it is not
true that every set of coordinates that
you could think of the interval is
expressed in the same way let me give
you an example just from
ordinary space not space time but space
if I
take coordinates X and Y which are the
usual kind of uh uh sorry X and Y the
usual kind of cartisian coordinates then
yes the separation between two points is
just dx2 plus the
y^2 if I rotate the coordinates
to X Prime and Y Prime by a standard
rotation of coordinates then the same
interval is DX Prime S Plus d y Prime
squ but what if I do something dumb like
use coordinates use a coordinate
mesh where X and Y are not measured in
the same units X is measured in inches
and Y is measured in uh in in
meters I have a point XY and a point uh
X Plus DX and Y plus Dy what is the
distance between those two points it is
not dx2 + D y^2 why not because you're
measuring the interval in uh uh in
different uh in different units in
particular supposing I wanted the
distance in inches let's see let let me
uh let me do let me let me use
centimeters here
centimeters and
meters centimeters and meters I don't
like factors of 12 and factors of 144
factors of 10 are easier all right
supposing I want the distance between
neighboring points but I want to measure
it in centimeters in centimeters this
this is X and this is y what is the
distance between two points it is it is
not the X2 + the y^2 but it's the X S
Plus Dy
/ 100
squared y over 100 well it's obvious
that if you use the same unit for y as
for x and you're measuring things in
cenm then it would be dx2 + D y^2 but if
I use meters for the vertical axis here
and I want to get back to centimeters I
better divide the Y component of vectors
by 100
all right so we could rewrite this then
it's dx^
2 plus 1 over 100 2 1 over
10,000 to
y^2 so if I do something stupid like use
awkward coordinates in where X and Y are
not measured in the same
units then my expression for distance is
going to have a form which will contain
some funny numbers in it like one over
100 th 10,000 here in particular it
won't be the nice symmetric dx2 + D
y^2 I go a little further supposing I
don't use orthogonal coordinates
supposing I decide to choose coordinates
in the following way I choose coordinate
axes which look like
that and now my rule is going to be the
coordinates of a point are gotten by
moving along the x- axis not to the
point where you drop a perpendicular but
where you draw a line parallel to the Y
AIS likewise the Y coordinat so this
would be the x coordinate and this would
be the
y-coordinate then the distance between
two points you don't have the standard
Pythagorean theorem anymore we have
triangles we have triangles now uh
here's X here's
y this is not a not a right
triangle so the hypot is not a
hypotenuse it's a uh just a third side
of a
triangle the length of this is
definitely not the x² plus the y^ squ
even if we use the same units on the X
and Y AIS it's just not true what uh
what is it what is it well I won't write
down precisely what the formula is but
it will always be of the form of some
coefficient
dx2 plus another coefficient Dy Square
let me not call it
D let's call it a b and c
a some number b d y^
2 but then what's new about coordinate
systems which have angles in them like
this which are not rectangular which are
not perpendicular is that there are
additional terms we can call them C time
DX
Dy
products of different uh coordinates
that's what
happens if you have coordinate systems
which are not orthogonal which are not
orthogonal coordinates off diagonal
elements like that you can also write
this in another way you can write it C
over2 *
dxdy plus C over2 *
dydx and so you have a whole bunch of uh
um
coefficients we could give these
coefficients names we could call this
one one for the fact that it multiplies
d x squared we could call this
22 well let's not let's why why are we
giving them different names we could
just call it
a22 or a y y this one we could call
axy and this one we could call a
YX notice that ax Y and a YX are exactly
the same thing I simply took the
coefficient of dxdy and split it between
two terms one which is DX Dy and the
other which is dydx just to symmetrize
it just to make it nice and
symmetric
finally I could display these
coefficients a as a matrix a11
a uh one well XY one two 2
1 a12 a21
a22 just display them as a metric as a
uh as a matrix in fact the Matrix is
called the
metric and this metric completely
encapsulates what the distance between
neighboring pairs of points are in terms
of four coefficients laid out as a
matrix this Matrix is called the
metric now if we're dealing with
ordinary space of the Blackboard flat
space uniform space everywhere the
same and we choose our
coordinates let's say at an
angle but we choose them by marking off
distances which are
equal along the x- axis
distances which are equal all along the
Y
AIS then these coefficients will just be
constants they'll be constants
because uh there'll be constants all
over the plane here again if we did
something foolish like decide to use
coordinates which lump up over here and
have a very different spacing another
other words where the spa the coordinate
spacing by one the horizontal axis here
is X this is x = 1 this is xal 2 this is
X = 3 4 5 6 we've made the coordinate
mesh very
non-uniform then it's completely obvious
that these A's will not be constants
because depending on where you are the
coordinate mesh might uh be finer or
coarser and so forth
and the result of that will be that in
general if you use arbitrary coordinates
crazy coordinates which are curved in
all kinds of complexity where the
spacing between coordinates is
non-uniform then the general rule will
be these coefficients will be functions
of
position what functions of position not
any functions of position if we're
talking about the flat
plane but a fairly a fairly wide class
of
functions can describe the interval
between two points in what I could call
crazy coordinates coordinates which have
curved axes and which uh which are
nonuniform but nevertheless the basic
geometry of the Blackboard is determined
by knowing the distance between between
every pair of neighboring points where
the points could be uh described by
coordinates X and
Y all right the same thing is true in
special
relativity that if you use the right
kind of coordinates that means
coordinates obtained by Lorent
transformation from each other then the
SpaceTime interval between two points is
always of the same type always of the
same form
if you use some cattywampus coordinates
which are
curved which nobody can prevent you from
doing I mean we can always use any
coordinates we like then the general
formula will be very very similar to
what we've written here and I'm going to
write it down the general formula in any
coordinates of exactly the same quantity
would be D Squared is some set of
coefficients and they're usually called
gunu of position all all the uh there'll
generally be functions of position and
then you'll have the X mu DX
new just in case it was not obvious this
can also be written as a i j the x i the
XJ summed over I and
J
so this is a very very general way of
writing the SpaceTime interval between
an arbitrary po pair of points and if
you know what gunu is then you know the
space-time geometry
completely if you know the space-time
geometry completely that does not
determine what G muu is why not because
you could always go and change
coordinates you could always go and
change the coordinates in SpaceTime in
some peculiar way and change what G muu
is so G muunu determines the SpaceTime
but the space the the geometric
properties of it the distance between
neighboring points and so forth but not
the other way the geometry doesn't
completely determine what gunu
is okay any questions about the the
symbols on the Blackboard thus far this
is just a more General way of writing
the spatial and temporal relationship
between
points and of course there are many
possibilities for the choice of the
functions G mu new of
X okay now let's go back to ordinary
space but imagine a space which is not
as flat as the
Blackboard which is
curved let me first tell you what curved
doesn't
mean if I take this piece of paper
here
and stretch it out nice and flat on the
surface here we'll all agree that that
piece of paper is
flat relations between points for
example the fact that uh
that triangles have angles which add up
to 180° and so forth that's all
determined by knowing the relationship
between distances of neighboring points
now I take this piece of paper and I
bend it nice and gently into a let's say
into a cylinder or let's not close it up
let's just uh bend it in some way like
that I haven't stretched it I have not
stretched it I've only bent it okay that
is not what's called curved in fact most
explicitly if you take a flat piece of
paper and deform it without anywhere
stretching it you don't change the you
don't change the distance between any
pair of neighboring points the distance
along the piece of paper the distance
being calculated moving by a little tiny
um insect moving along the piece of
paper would not
change why not because I haven't
stretched anything in fact a creature
that lives on this piece of paper that
can't look off the
paper uh can't look on one side can't
look on the other side only is aware of
motion within the piece of paper would
not detect
the fact that we bent the piece of paper
every pair of points would have exactly
the same distance as it had
before
and mathematicians do not refer to this
process as curving of
space curving of a space is what
happens
when you cannot flatten it out on the
surface here without deforming it
without stretching it without changing
the distance between neighboring points
so for example if I took a hemisphere of
rubber not a hemisphere not a solid
hemisphere of rubber a surface like the
surface of a
balloon and I tried
to let's cut the balloon in half so it's
only a
hemisphere and I tried to put it down on
the table here without stretching it
obviously I can't do it I would have to
take the boundary of the semicircular of
the circular uh of the circular boundary
of the piece of the balloon that I
captured and I'd have to stretch it I'd
probably have to squeeze the center of
it to push it down onto the
plane and
uh that distinction
between bending we'll call it and
curvature real curvature curvature is
that which is there when you cannot
deform something to make it flat without
stretching it that's called curvature
all right again if I take some curved sp
Let me give you an example a sphere is a
very good example of the surface of a
sphere is a very good example of a
curved space you cannot flatten a sphere
onto a plane without stretching or
deforming it and that's of
course known to you all that uh that
that's the reason that you can't draw
maps that uh that don't stretch
Greenland and make it huge and uh and um
Greenland on a marcada projection looks
as big as Africa it's only about one
tenth the size in area and uh it's
because the sphere is curved it's
fundamentally curved
now the SpaceTime or the spatial
distances let's go back to space
distances of a sphere let's take a
sphere we can coordinate we can put
coordinates on a sphere such as the
coordinates on the surface of the Earth
longitude and latitude they angles one
can be called
Theta the other can be called fi polar
and uh and azimuthal angles you can also
Express the distance between neighboring
points on the sphere in terms of uh in
terms of little differential expressions
like this the main
difference
or the uh the fact is no way of
coordinatization eents of the metric
constant in space if they're constant in
space it means at worst your coordinate
axes are tilted relative to each other
but nevertheless the space is flat if
it's impossible to find coordinates
where you can flatten out where you can
uh where you can represent the metric as
being constant then you have a
fundamentally curved surface that you
cannot flatten out so curvature is an OB
struction to flattening out a surface
and uh
and making the metric a constant
Matrix that's the notion of
curvature in practice the examples we're
going to do are very
simple uh let me give you a nice example
of
a funny set of coordinates that you can
use on the
plane polar coordinates you all know
what polar coordinates are I hope you
represent points by angles Theta and
Radial distance
R okay supposing I want to talk about
the distance of
um well let's
see yeah
um
yeah let's take a interval here this is
some Dr and some D
Theta what is the distance between this
point in this point I'm going to write
it down I'm going to write down the
answer for you you can check it yourself
the answer is very simple it's the R
2 plus r 2 D Theta
2 why is it R 2 D Theta squar the Theta
now is just the uh the change in angle
between these two points
all right you draw yourself a little
right triangle here one side of which is
Dr
R but the other side is not D Theta for
a given D Theta the further out you move
the bigger the side of that triangle the
side of this triangle here is not D
Theta it's r d
Theta so Pythagoras's Theorem tells you
that this is Dr r^ 2 + r 2 D Theta 2 is
an example where the coefficients of the
metric are not constant isn't it
R sin D no r sarea s you're thinking
about a
sphere Thea is in radians yeah okay
Theta is in radians no there's no sign
there so is that what you ask me if it's
a sign it seems like for small things
it's it's a it
it would reduce the D Theta but for no
no no no no no no no no no no no no
matter how small D Theta is no matter
how small D Theta is if you go far away
the distance
grows so the distance along the D Theta
side here is proportional to
R
yeah yeah R that's right AR length is
always r d
thet and so now we have a metric which
we can display in The Matrix form one
over here the R 2 R 2 over here
multiplying the Theta squ 0 0 so here's
an an in a simple example of a
coordinate system where the flat
Blackboard is displayed with a metric
which is not constant
everywhere okay
but what I can do is revert back to uh
to X and Y coordinates X
= R cosine Theta y = r sin Theta rewrite
this expression and lo and behold it
just becomes dx2 + D
y^2 in which case the metric in these
coordinates is just good old 1 1 0
0 so the flat plane
or the fact that this is a flat plane
may not be so obvious when it's
displayed in this peculiar way here not
the X S Plus the y^ S but r s the r s d
Theta squ um but nevertheless the fact
that you can find coordinates the
flatten it out means that the Blackboard
is flat even though you've displayed it
in some curvy linear funny coordinate
frame on the other hand if you would
take take a
sphere if you were to take a sphere
let's work
out the metric on a
sphere all right we have one coordinate
which I guess is called polar angle and
it's the angular distance along the
sphere let's take some arbitrary
point over
here you
go what's the uh latitude right latitude
is the angle from the equator I'm going
to take it to be the angle from the
north latitude yeah latitude is the
angle from the equator I'm going to just
allow it to be angle from the North Pole
for Simplicity they differ by 90° and
the other and the other variable is um
as a muthal angle which is uh let's see
we call this one D Theta and the other
one
D supposing I take two neighboring
points on the
sphere characterized by a dtheta or the
the interval being characterized by D
Theta and D there it is D Theta is this
much is this side of a right triangle
and
defi characterizes this side of the
triangle
now let's suppose for Simplicity that
this is a unit sphere that means a
sphere of radius one just for Simplicity
if it's a sphere of radius one how far
is it then Theta simply measures
distance along the sphere if I tell you
to walk along a line of constant
latitude a line of constant latitude
from no a line of constant longitude
excuse me a line of constant
longitude and I tell you to walk a
certain number of
degrees or a certain number of radians
then the distance that you walk is
absolutely proportional to the angle to
the number of
radians okay and it doesn't matter where
you are the same number of radians
corresponds to the same distance so for
the unit
sphere The Arc distance along
the along the dtheta direction is
just d
Theta that's the distance along the
Theta and so we're going to use
Pythagoras's Theorem and tells us that
the distance along the s s is D Theta
squar but what about d^ squ is Def the
actual distance along the other leg of
the triangle here no defy up near the
North Pole a given defi up near the
North Pole corresponds to a small
interval down near the equator the same
fi the same fi interval is a larger
distance as we go all the way down to
the South Pole it gets small
again in
fact the horizontal
size of the
triangle is let's write it over here is
Def times s of
theta
when you're up at the North Pole the
sign of theta is very small Theta is
equal to zero up at the North Pole it's
also equal to zero down near the South
Pole s not Theta isn't S of theta is
zero down near the South Pole this is
actually the distance s of theta time D
is the distance
along the horizontal segment here then
using Pythagoras's Theorem we would
discover that the distance between
neighboring points is D Theta s
plus sin Theta 2 d^
2 this is the metric of a sphere a
two-dimensional sphere D Theta 2 plus
sin 2 d^ 2 it's the metric in the usual
azimuthal and polar coordinates of the
longitude and
latitude what if this were not a sphere
of radius one what about if it was a
sphere of radius r
then the only difference would be we
would multiply the whole thing by R
2ar since this is the square of a
distance it ought to be quadratic in the
radius of the sphere so if we double the
size of the sphere we double every
length and that means the square of this
length would get multiplied by
four so for a sphere of radius R we've
now worked out what the metric tensor is
and the metric tensor would be R
2 R 2 sin Theta
2ar Sin Sin Theta squar 0
0 so again this is not so different from
The Polar coordinates let me just remind
you for the polar coordinates we had uh
forget with Dr s+ R 2 um the Theta
squar no this that's sort of similar
there's
a uh
there's a term which is constant and
there's then there's a term down here
which depends on S of
theta somewhat
similar okay this metric can never be
flattened out there is no set of
coordinates that you can find to
coordinati the sphere so that you make
the coefficients of the metric tensor
constant impossible to do that's simply
because you cannot flatten the sphere
onto a plane without stretching it uh if
you and so this is a fundamentally
curved surface the fact that it's a
curved surface could be detected by
creatures moving around on the surface
without ever leaving the surface so
without ever looking along the surface
for example they would discover that
triangles on the
surface have the sum of their angles
larger than 180° and that's because the
triangle sort of bow out bow bow
out uh making the sum of the angles
larger so a creature would walk as
straight as he could along a
line make a angular turn over here make
another angular turn come back to the
same point and discover that the sum of
the angles of his closed triangle would
not be
180° okay so that uh and therefore would
discover that he lived on a curved
surface without ever leaving the surface
without ever getting off it and seeing
that it was bent in some higher
dimensional
sense that's the notion of a metric
tensor that's the notion of distance or
between neighboring points points and
it's the notion of curvature which I'm
not going to work out a mathematical
expression for
curvature sufficient for our purposes
just to say if a space is curved you
cannot get rid of the
variation the variation from point to
point in the coefficient of the metric
tensor
um same thing is true in
SpaceTime
and that was the new ingredient that
Einstein introduced into the general
theory of
relativity the idea that the proper time
between
points first of all can be represented
by a metric tensor a metric tensor which
varies in space now that in itself is
nothing new why because even if you took
ordinary flat SpaceTime and expressed it
in funny coordinates you could make the
tensor vary from point to point but the
new ingredient was that SpaceTime can be
curved curved means that there is no way
to undo no better choice of coordinates
where you can undo the fact that the
metric of space time varies from point
to
point
uh I'm not going to take you deeply into
the general theory of relativity what
we're going to do is explore one or two
simple geometric situations that come up
in
cosmology
and I'm not even going to derive I'm
going to Simply State what the geometry
of various kinds of cosmologies are and
then explore them a little bit and see
what kind of a world we live
in
now we're talking about SpaceTime we're
not just talking about space but space
time the kind of cosmologies that I'm
going to be interested in are
cosmologies which are time dependent
which don't vary from point to point in
space in other words where every point
in space is exactly the same as every
other point that's of course not true if
you're in the middle of a star it's
quite different than being uh in
somewhere as an Interstellar space
but on the whole the universe is
homogeneous which means the same from
point to point some facts let's write
down some facts about the
Universe on the whole the universe is
homogeneous homogeneous does not mean
flat as an example of a geometry which
is homogeneous we have the sphere the
sphere at every point is the same at as
at every every other point so it's a
homogeneous geometry but it's not a flat
geometry homogeneous means homogeneous
in space from point to point in space
not in SpaceTime things change with time
the universe grows so homogeneous in
space look like some points have matter
in other points are yeah yeah but on the
whole meaning on scales larger than the
intergalactic separation Things Are are
pretty homogeneous right so can can I
pursue that just a little what's that
can I pursue that yeah just a little
sure because this has puzzled me I mean
I know about this assumption what have
you but then you'll see let's say in
Scientific American or something you'll
see some picture that says that the
galaxies are strung out and there's
these stringy structures yes yes yes you
just have to get that's still small
scale structure that's still small scale
structure yeah yeah on yeah yeah yeah
okay so let's uh we can talk about size
scales on scales of a couple hundred
million light years and remember the the
universe is 10 billion light
years the portion of it that can be seen
so on a scale
of oh 100 million light years maybe a
few hundred million light years uh
things flatten out so that's a tenth so
that's a 100th size on a scale of 100th
of the size of the observable universe
everything becomes rather
homogeneous now we look through
telescopes and we can see that the
Universe various all kinds of telescopes
the universe does not seem to come to an
end anywhere as it just seems to go on
and on so as far as we know it's a lot
bigger not as far as we know we know
that it's a lot bigger than the portion
we can
see and so on some sufficiently large
scale uh it appears to be homogeneous or
largely
homogeneous uh now that could change
that could change some astronomical
observation might discover particularly
in the microwave background on the
biggest scales in the sky it might be
discovered that there is a little bit of
variation across the left hemisphere
might look a little different than the
right hemisphere that could happen this
is not a principle of the despite the
fact that it's called the cosmological
principle it doesn't mean it's a
principle of thought that could that
that has has to be true it could change
all right but um at the moment as far as
we can tell the universe is pretty
homogeneous on large enough scales and
we're going to deal with it on large
scales the second F fact is that space
not space time let's distinguish space
and space time space at any given
Instinct okay on large enough scales is
flat what that means is is if you take
at an instant of time in the expanding
Universe you take a triangle any
triangle composed out of the straightest
lines that you can make straight lines
in fact that the sum of the angles of
the triangle add up to
180° that all the spatial relations at
an instant of time are consistent with
space being flat now that yes can you
actually talk about large areas of space
and all at the same time that's doesn't
make sense well
um look you can you can talk about small
areas of space makees
sense well we been talking about I I
know what you're saying you can collect
you cannot you cannot at an instant of
time know anything about three points
which are separated by a large distance
but you can let's let's let's draw
SpaceTime here SpaceTime time is
vertical space is horizontal all right
so here's three points in space at the
same instant of time one two and the
third one forms some triangle back over
here okay so if we happen to look at the
world at the same instant of time there
is no way that we can see all three
points okay but we can collect data
later from the three points and by
collecting data from the three
points um we can correlate information
about the triangle and moreover we can
collect it from different
perspectives and then bring our signals
together and learn a great deal by
looking back at this triangle learn a
great deal about what we uh What uh what
the shape of that triangle was at that
instant of time so it's correct you
cannot you cannot know anything
basically you can't know about anything
except right now here and now now but
you can collect signals and in fact I
can't know anything about you right at
this instant of time I can only know
about you at an instant of time over
which light has been able to Signal same
thing throw here so we can look back and
correlate data and uh and that of course
is what we do when we look out into the
sky and make measurements of galaxies
and this they're all a little bit
indirect but when we make geometric
statements we're making statements about
looking back in the sky and deducing
what the uh what the geometry of space
must have
been right so the second statement it's
homogeneous everywhere the
same but more than that space space is
flat that's not the same as space time
space flat is
space flat is space subtle is the
Lord rightward H right
[Laughter]
backward FL space look at
it
but it's time dependent and as time goes
on if you follow two points what does it
mean to follow two points follow two
Galaxies for example as time goes on the
distance between those galaxies
increases with time
okay there's a standard description of
such A Spacetime one which is expanding
as time goes
on but which is homogeneous and which is
flat and it's rather simple it's easy to
understand at least I hope it's easy to
understand uh it's described in terms of
a space-time metric a proper
time first of all it's described in
terms of coordinates so we take the
usual
coordinates X Y and Z and add to it t x
y and z and
T it's just like special relativity
SpaceTime except the metric tensor is
more complicated in fact let's uh let's
see what we can deduce from the fact
that space is everywhere is the same and
that it's flat we can deduce that at any
given instant of time we can find
coordinates where which just allow it to
be
represented in terms of cartisian
coordinates all right so that
means that we can expect that it be of
the form dx2 plus d y^2 plus dz^2 the
distance between two
points but we should account for the
fact remember incidentally that in the
special theory of relativity space comes
in with a negative sign
so we should really put in here
minuses just like in special theory of
relativity but we should possibly take
into
account uh a question of
units if you were
to measure space in centimeters but ask
for the distance between points in
meters or kilometers or
miles the only difference would be that
you would multiply this by some
conversion factor and let's call that
conversion factor
a
squared in other words if we
were measuring let's measure the
distance between okay let's measure the
distance between
points
by the number of
galaxies along a more or less straight
line
between two points here we have two
points in the universe far from each
other there are many galaxies in
between and roughly speaking the
distance between galaxies is all the
same about about two million light years
between neighboring
galaxies okay roughly speaking and I'm
I'm going to be rough on purpose and we
simply represent the coordinates of
these particles by asking how many
galaxies are there Galactic spacings are
there between
them well since the galaxies separate
with time at different
times this measure of distance will
correspond to actual different measures
in meters and for that reason we have to
keep track of the fact that our
coordinates may be we may be working in
units at a given time which are not
meters which are not
centimeters but which correspond to a
measure corresponding to some uh number
of galaxies between points or whatever
so we throw in a factor it's simply a
conversion factor a unit conversion
factor from whatever the units of x y
and z are to actual physical distances
let's say in
meters this a here is constant in
space it doesn't vary from point to
point in space it may vary in time it
might vary in time for example if the
galaxies are separating let's call this
point xal 1 let's call this point xal 2
it's just the name of the points this
point out here a little further out
that's xal minus1 and we actually make a
a three-dimensional array
a coordinate patch in space which
expands with the galactic
expansion right in other words we look
out we discover that the galaxies are
separating from each other we imagine
some coordinates which are rectangular
cartisian
coordinates but the
coordinate are spreading together with
the flow of the galaxies as the galaxies
expand or as the space expands
the distance between neighboring points
in this grid is growing that's this AF
here and this AF does not depend on
where you are in space that's the
statement that space is flat the fact
that space is flat means that space can
always be represented by a constant set
of coefficients and in fact those
constant set of coefficients can be
taken to be of the uh of the ordinary
cartisian
kind okay that's space What About Time
time is exactly as it is in special
theory of relativity dt^
2qu dt^
s let's write it this way let me rewrite
it d^ 2 is equal to dt^ 2 same as in
special relativity plus or
minus
some function of time which represents
the expansion of the universe it
increases with time times the usual the
X2 plus the y^2 plus the z^
2 so this kind of
metric represents here you can see
here's the
galaxies okay and we imagine a mesh of
coordinates embedded with the galaxies
but as the galaxies expand the
coordinate mesh expands with them that
means that the coordinates that we
assign to the galaxies don't change with
time the G the fact that this is the
Galaxy at Point xal 1 xal 0 and Y = 1
this is the Galaxy at x = 5 and yal 7
that is preserved with time because the
coordinate mesh increases with the
universe but we have to account for this
expansion
we have to account for the fact that the
distance is actually expanding with time
and that's done by a Time dependence in
the coefficient here anybody know what
this thing is called
aft no no it's not a constant it's
called the scale
factor it's called the scale factor and
it's a thing which does not as I said
depend on space but it does depend on
time and it represents the fact that any
fixed points in space fixed meaning to
say that they have fixed coordinates
that the distance between them increases
in time this is the
basic uh setup for essentially all of
observational
cosmology that the universe is described
by a metric which looks like this all
right so let me first tell you a couple
of things
about ask a question
yeah I don't know if this is the best
time for it but it's always bothering
what you talked about is we have two
galaxies well lots of galaxies galaxies
and uh their metric Remains the Same uh
well their position space Remains the
Same because the distance between them
uh between the two points changes but
they're right but that that's okay
that's the AF changes but the other is
not right the position is labeled to
same right labels that's right think of
x's as just labels lab in the points but
if this is true with galaxies it's also
been true with the meter stick no the
meter stick does not expand with the
expansion but what well that's my point
What's the difference between two
galaxies and the end of a meter stick
the the meter stick is held together by
molecular
bonds meter stick is held together by
electromagnetic bonds which are strong
enough to overcome the expansion of the
universe right it's good very good
question but galy expand the gala
galaxies are not not expanding see um
galaxies are small enough and
concentrated enough that their own
gravity holds them together and in fact
even causes them to shrink with time a
little bit right a star shrinks with
time uh the distance between galaxies on
the average is large enough that the
gravitational interactions between them
are fairly negligible and so they sort
of uh they expand with the ambient
background expansion but the individual
galaxies are small enough that gravity
is pulling them together okay so it's a
it's an awkward situation where uh where
some scales of mass and
distance are such that things are being
pulled together and other scales of
distance and mass are such that uh that
um
uh that things are basically just
flowing with the flow has that worked
out I mean in detail not by me I you
know that absolutely that these forces
are counterbalancing those and so
absolutely
yeah great in great detail so I mean
people could just say well the strength
of this interaction is this and the
gravitational okay but in the process of
doing that a discovery was made that
things weren't the way people thought
they discovered that there has to be
more mass in a galaxy holding it
together than the apparent mass that you
see through telescopes in the Sky by
looking at Optical light and that of
course was the discovery of dark uh Dark
Matter not dark energy but dark
matter right but once that's accounted
for once you do it once in one Galaxy do
it another time in another
galaxy uh and you do a whole bunch of
crosscorrelations and checks and so
forth once you've done that you know
that gravity is strong enough within a
Galaxy to hold it together not strong
enough within uh neighboring galaxies to
keep them from uh now that that of
course there are some
exceptions
um our neighboring Galaxy the Andromeda
just happens to be close enough and
heavy enough and we're heavy enough that
the force of attraction of gravity
happens to be pulling them that happens
to be causing them to fall toward each
other all right just happens that those
are two unusually massive galaxies at
not too large a distance and so there's
sort of an exception in galaxies that
are coming together but on the average
the galaxies are moving apart and on a
scale large enough that uh that uh
gravity is weak enough they're just all
separating from each
other what's that are in number G oh
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah neighboring
galaxies that no no it's not certainly
not ni ated example but on the average
even neighboring galaxies tend to be
moving apart from each
other why don't they consider it a force
a
what why don't they consider it a force
a forth a force force because um it
seems that it kind of behaves like a
force what does the the scale factor or
well
you
um well let's be precise I mean let's be
prec prise a uh uh a scale factor is not
a force a scale factor is a scale factor
it has units of a length it doesn't have
units of a force I mean I'm not sure
what you mean by say call it a force you
mean could it be due to some Force
that's causing things to
uh
uh let's
let's
the okay so let's let's not uh let's not
worry about Force for the moment later
on we'll come to the effect of
gravitational force and how it affects
things but uh yeah it is it is it is
like it is due to gravity I mean
solution better for so
it's it's the thing let's put it this
way you see a um you you shoot an object
from the surface of the Earth Cannon
Cannonball except very very fast uh
50,000 M an hour or whatever is that
pass greater than escap
get escape velocity and you see it
moving out moving out moving out moving
out is Gravity the thing that's causing
it to move
out it's inertia that's causing it to
move out in a sense now the original
shot that shot it out that's not a that
that is uh not the statement of inertia
but once it's been shot out by whatever
mechanism shot it out the fact that the
earth and the Cannonball are receding
from each other is not due to any Force
I mean it's the mistake Aristotle made
to think that motion is due to force
it's due to inertia okay on the other
hand uh really there's a second thing
that's going on as the cannon ball moves
out it
decelerates the force of gravity
decelerates it it may be enough to
decelerate it and make it fall back or
it may not be enough to decelerate it
and cause it to fall back depending but
but in either case it decelerates Ates
it the force of gravity causes the
velocity to change with time of course
ASM totically if it really does escape
then it keeps going with a uniform
velocity approximately but as it's
moving apart it it decelerates the
universe is just like that there's an
expansion okay and until recently it was
thought that that expansion is
decelerating the expansion is like
shooting an explosion out of a cannon
where what keeps it going is not a force
what keeps it going is just
inertia but it was expected that that
inertia would be fought by the
gravitational attraction be between
things not necessarily that it meant
that things would fall back in but that
they would be slowly decelerating so the
expansion would be decelerating that
turned out not to be true but uh let's
uh let's say what we can say on the
basis of these things all right let's
talk about the expansion and the
distance the time dependence let's take
a pair of
galaxies are that are separated by a
certain distance let's take them to be
along the x-axis for
Simplicity uh two galaxies along the
x-axis they don't have to be along the
xaxis I'm just taking it for Simplicity
along the
x-axis and let's take the
separation between them the coordinate
separation not the actual distance but
the coordinate
separation and call it Delta
X Delta X does not change with
time Delta X remember the coordinates
are embedded and expanding so if this is
x = 1 and this is xal 5 forever and ever
eternally from now on this galaxy is at
xal 1 this galaxy is at x = 5 Delta X is
4 and it will stay that way forever but
let's not specify it let's just call it
Delta X what's the distance the actual
numerical distance in meters for example
or whatever units we use
between x equals between those two
points to find it we have to multiply by
a a is the conversion factor from these
labels which are simply labels to actual
metrical distances measured in whatever
units uh whatever physical units we like
I'll I'll talk about meters I'll use the
the units meters all right so the actual
distance is a * Delta X and let's call
that d d for distance that's the actual
and and a is a function of
time okay what's the velocity of
recession between those two how fast are
they separating from each other in me/
second the answer to that is
simple we just differentiate D with
respect to time D is the distance if we
differentiate it with respect to time
for these two points then that'll give
us the velocity between them now Delta
that's fixed Delta is just four units in
the case of xal 1 and xal 5 it never
changes so when we differentiate with
respect to time the only only thing that
changes is a a the expansion factor is
increasing it has a
derivative and so we can say that the
velocity which is the time derivative or
speed the speed of expansion between two
points is just equal to the time
derivative of a I'm going to use the
notation that time derivative is just
putting a DOT on top of a thing time
derivative is often I think we've
probably used that before I hope we have
but if not
DOT means d by
DT so this is the time derivative of a
Time Delta X that's the
velocity
okay well let me do a little trick with
this let me multiply it and divide
it by
a what is Delta x *
a that's D the
distance so I've derived very simply a
very simple rule that the velocity of
separate the velocity of recession
between two objects is proportional to
the distance between
them times something which doesn't
depend on where you are it depends on
when you are but not where you are a DOT
over a remember a does not depend on
position in space it does depend on
time a DOT ided
a all right a DOT ided a is the
coefficient relating velocity to
distance there another name for a. over
a Hubble the Hubble expansion
uh usually sometimes called the Hubble
constant but it's quite obvious that in
general a do over a is not a constant in
general it depends on
time a and a dot in general both depend
on time and so the Hubble expansion rate
the thing that's usually called Capital
H
velocity is
distance time H but H is nothing but the
ratio
IO of a of the time derivative of a to a
itself most important fact about it is
that it doesn't depend on where you are
it doesn't depend on which pair of
galaxies you're talking about every pair
of galaxies at a particular instant of
time will re will recess from each other
will have a recession or a velocity of
of Separation which is proportional to
the
distance and multipli by the Hubble
constant or the Hubble parameter I think
we should call the Hubble parameter yeah
uh a is dependent upon T and if you have
very very wide the separated galaxies
can use the same key at a g at a given
instant of time
yes right right right no you're perfect
what you're asking I think is the right
question if you look back and you see a
galaxy far enough away all right far
enough away and you want to and you
measure its expansion should you use a
do over a today or should you use it
then the answer is then right so yeah
but uh typically a do over a is changing
relatively slowly in time so that large
large pieces of the universe the Hubble
constant doesn't change very much with
time but that's that is taken into
account when people look at the
recessional velocities that the
recessional velocities have to be
slightly modified from this formula to
account for the difference of time that
you're actually looking at things so
that's a good point one more question uh
it's a question of dimensions in this
detail a squ a has a Dimensions the
length have let's use Cal 1 first of all
let's use C equals 1 first of all so
that time and space have the same
dimensions yeah so
yeah yeah no no no no think of x
as not having any Dimensions at all
they're just labels they're names Fred
Charlie and and so forth xal 1 xal 2 x
three carry completely
dimensionless uh of course there is
that's that's somewhat ambiguous you
could choose a to be dimensionist and
let X have units of length that's
somewhat arbitrary I like to think of it
as just saying the X's label the points
and don't carry any dimensions and the
dimensions of distance are in a so
that's that's again another good point
okay this is the Hubble
law velocity at any given instant of
time is proportional to distance with
the Hubble constant itself with the
Hubble constant itself is it
surprising no what it says is the
fastest the faster you move the further
you get that's all really that's all it
says the faster you move the further you
get so uh as things uh if things are
moving fast the further apart but
there's a detailed form that uh that uh
it's called the Hubble
law when you think about it it really
could hardly be any other way well
actually I guess you could uh you could
contrive but not with these set of
assumptions here the Hubble law is just
very
general in special relativity
light
satisfies D equals
z along a light
Ray along the interval of a light Ray DX
Dy DZ DT and so forth the proper time is
zero why is it zero let's move along the
x-axis in units in which the speed of
light is
one then DX will equal
DT if the speed of light of course if
the speed of light is then it's DX equal
CDT but if C is set equal to 1 as they
are in all my
equations then DX equal DT and DT ^2
minus dx^ 2 =
0 so a light Ray is a peculiar path
through
SpaceTime where the proper time along
the path along the path of the light Ray
is zero that characterizes the motion of
a light Ray that the proper distance
along the light Ray or the proper time
along the right light Ray is
zero knowing that and assuming that it's
true in the general theory of relativity
which it is we can read off from this
let's suppose there's a light Ray moving
along the x-axis if we get Y and
Z then what is the equation of the light
Ray the equation of the light Ray is
just a detail equals z or that
DT equals a of t
*
DX uh we could write that another way we
could divide by a if we
like did I do that
right
yes all right so a
lightray moves with a DX that's not just
given by DT but DT divided by a of
T this makes it look in the coordinates
that we're using as though a light Ray
slows down with time why a gets bigger
and bigger um this says that the
velocity of the light Ray DX by DT
shrinks with time
now what's really going on is not that
the light Ray is slowing down is that if
you go far enough away things are moving
out faster and faster and so from your
perspective but but this is what a light
rate
does this
is uh the motion of a light Ray in these
coordinates which remember these
coordinates are not measured in
meters in these coordinates X simply
dimensionless and the light Ray moves an
amount of distance DX X in a given
amount of time it moves a distance which
depends on the scale factor so you keep
track of things
in cosmology by remembering that light
rays move on what are called null lines
null lines mean they have zero proper
time and you can calculate how a light
Ray would move through the space by
knowing that it's um DX is always equal
to DT divided by the uh by the scale
factor and the only reason the scale
factor is there is because as time goes
on a given DX corresponds to a larger
and larger
separation it would be crazy if the
light Ray always moved with the
same DX for a given DT because at late
times a given DX is a huge huge
distance
so that's taken care of by putting AF of
down squares here so that's the that's
the motion of a light Ray and we could
calculate if we knew what AF of is for a
particular situation we could calculate
the motion of a light
Ray
uh so this is the SpaceTime
geometry
aft of certainly not the general Rel the
general SpaceTime geometry of general
relativity but it is on the whole
The Fairly General description of almost
all versions that I know of of uh of of
large scale cosmology cosmology on a
scale large enough that uh that you can
ignore the variations from point to
point it's more complicated if space
were curved space could be a sphere it
could be a hyperb oid it could be
something else fortunately space appears
really to be flat the x² plus the y s
plus the z s which makes the formulas
rather
easy
okay the next question we can ask lots
and lots of questions just about this
geometry but the most fundamental
question that we might want to ask is
what is AF how does it vary with time
how does AF does it grow and then
shrink does it keep growing does it grow
as a power of time does it grow as the
logarithm of time does it grow if it
grows exponentially with time does it
how does it behave right that is
determined by gravitational force and
gravitational
Dynamics it's roughly the same question
or a version of the question of if you
see a missile moving away from you how
does it move away from you with time
that depends on its equations of motion
it depends on gravitational Dynamics it
depends on f equals Ma and all that
stuff so that becomes the next question
how does AFT vary with time going to
work that out for one
example well I think maybe we'll work it
out for two
examples but
uh why is that question any more
important than
is the charge of electron vary with time
or or qu it's not more important than
the question of whether the charge of
electron varies with time we seem to
focus on that question though we seem to
focus on whether aft varies of time
though whether the UN that's because we
know that AF varies with time and we
also are pretty damn sure the charge of
the electron doesn't if the charge of
the electron started varying with time
and we noticed it uh we would consider
that awfully
important uh right but from a from a
geometric point of view from the point
of view of the geometry of
SpaceTime a not the only question but a
central question would be how AF varies
with time if AF didn't vary with time we
would have just plain old flat SpaceTime
we could get rid of this a by changing
the units of
X by changing the units of X we could
get rid of this a if it didn't vary with
time only because it varies with time uh
does the SpaceTime have a um
a non-trivial
geometry it would just be plain old flat
SpaceTime if a was constant with
time all right uh I did not mean to
imply that that that the variation of a
with with time is necessarily the most
important question of
cosmology uh but let me tell you if we
discovered a didn't vary with time we
might not change Atomic physics very
much and we might not change particle
physics very much but we would sure as
hell change cosmology uh to be something
totally unrecognizable from the present
uh
perspective we're not I'm not going to
talk about the way that you
experimentally detect the recession of
velocities and so forth that's
uh a different
topic it seems like that always gets
rushed over and that depends on sey
variable stars and that's depends on all
sorts of
physics okay it's just too
complicated but before you yeah but you
see before you can start thinking about
actually how you really do measure
it uh you really have to have some
theory behind you to know what it is
you're
measuring um it's true you can measure
the local velocity of nearby by um
nearby galaxies and so forth without
being too sophisticated but if you want
to measure the very very distant
galaxies then you have to worry for
example that the Hubble parameter
changes with time as you pointed out so
you better have some basic theoretical
structure to begin with before you can
even ask the
questions uh or basic geometric setup
we're talking about the geometric setup
and not the
[Music]
um not the way of
measuring space-time distances and so
forth on astronomical scales besides I
suspect most of you have some idea of
how astronomy measures distances uh
velocities and so forth distance very
easy way to measure
distances uh the easiest way to measure
distances is uh to a distant Galaxy is
just to look at its luminosity in your
telescope if it's dim it's far if it's
bright it's
near uh and you use a simple law that
the uh that the uh Luminosity the
apparent Luminosity is like one over the
square of the distance because light
spreads out in a certain way that's the
dumbest and stupidest and probably
probably not the the best way to measure
distances to distant stars but roughly
speaking that gives you a pretty good
idea of how far distant galaxies are how
do you measure their velocity you
measure their velocity by the red shift
of their atomic uh uh trans positions by
the toppler shift and those two
together tell you the Hubble law that's
what Hubble did he didn't get it right
numerically he was off by a factor of 10
or something when on his own
constant uh incidentally there's an
interesting supposing the Hubble
constant were constant with time suppose
it really were
constant and
that
distances were related by a fixed number
H to
velocities okay then you could ask the
following question run it backward we
take two
galaxies a certain distance
apart run it backward they come together
how long does it take for them to come
together well that's easy you take let's
see what do you do you divide distance
um how long does it take rate the
distance uh I always have to I always
have to work this out distance equal
velocity time time yeah uh so how long
would it take for those two galaxies to
collide with each other if you ran it
backward well the answer is the distance
between them divided by their velocity
if the velocity were uniform in other
words if the Hubble constant were
actually
constant uh oh sorry not if the Hub not
if the Hubble constant were constant if
the velocities were constant if the
velocity of a given of this star out
here was constant with time and we ran
it backward we could ask how far in time
does it take before they collide with
each other I I I shouldn't have said if
the Hubble constant is constant that was
wrong if the velocity was constant in
other words if every Galaxy was receding
with a uniform velocity that didn't
change with time then how long would it
take for two galaxies to be on top of
each other the distance the answer would
be the distance between them divided by
the velocity but if the velocity is
equal to the distance time the Hubble
expansion parameter this reads
distance divided by H *
distance or just one over
H the inverse of the Hubble expansion
parameter is the time that it would take
if you ran the galaxies backward
for two neighboring or two distant
galaxies to be on top of each other
notice that that time doesn't depend on
which galaxies we're talking about it
doesn't depend on how far apart they are
right now because that cancels out what
remains is that the time is equal to one
over the so the bigger the Hubble
constant the less time it would take for
two uh if we ran it backwards for two
galaxies to collide with each other and
doesn't matter which galaxies you take
take any pair of galaxies they'll be
sitting on top of each other in a time
of order one over the H
expansion
but you're thinking of only two galaxies
and not the other folks coming in well
of course if any two of them are on top
of each other they'll all be on top of
each other so the model no sure might
crash yeah but this does give you some
estimate of uh how far back in time
before it crashes before it has to
crash um this incidentally is no
different really than saying if I look
out and I see something moving away from
me with a certain velocity and I know
it's distance I can roughly estimate how
long uh in the past it must have been
ejected if I see it moving with a
certain velocity and I know it's a
certain distance I can make a good guess
about how long ago it was sitting in my
lap on the earth so it's it's it's
really no different than that it's a
crude and rough estimate of how long ago
the Big Bang was by measuring the
velocity of distant
galaxies measuring their distance we get
the Hubble parameter the inverse of the
hubu parameter is we can call it the age
of the universe it's one measure of the
age of the universe nobody knows when
the universe began and how it began but
uh this inverse H is of order the time
to the Big Bang would you incidentally
expect
um what would you expect would you
expect the real time was shorter than
that or longer than
that longer
why because there might be
other
forces well we're not we haven't even
mentioned forces here this is what would
happen if the velocity was absolutely
uniform so okay so think about that
object that's moving away from us we
measure its velocity sometime in the
future we see it's moving away from us
with a certain speed and we want to know
how long ago it uh left the Earth well
we can answer that question by running
it backward take the uh take that same
object reverse its velocity and ask how
long it takes to fall into the Earth the
answer is less time than if it were
moving with uniform velocity because the
Earth attracts it and causes it to
accelerate toward the Earth it takes
less time so this in the standard
oldfashioned kind of cosmologies this
estimate of the uh of the age of the
universe was a little bit too long the
the universe would have to be less old
than
that
uh but not by a lot not by a
lot did you tell us that within our own
Galaxy there's no expansion going on
right so when you get to Galaxy links
well no right at some point this theory
has to
crash uh crash means exactly what as you
as you run backward or really the
backwards of what happened as you went
forward the Galaxy sort of materialized
out of fluctuations in a relative degree
of almost complete homogeneity by
attracting the matter attracting and
clumping and so forth uh I and I don't
think you would that is not what you
would see if you literally ran it
backwards if you run a real event
backward you don't get to see uh the uh
the backwards of the forward
motion um if
you yeah yeah yeah yeah right I mean you
know there's various ways to describe it
sometimes it's called the second law of
Thermodynamics sometimes it's called the
increase of entropy sometimes it's just
C happens you know
right when when we measure the distance
to
galaxies clearly we're we're measuring
in terms of some standard LS that we
have here on Earth compare that yes yes
so is there a physical
experiment that allows us to distinguish
whether these galaxies are
expanding or or that whether the
galaxies themselves are expanding
whether the AF is growing yeah say or
whether my ruler is shrinking no there's
no way to tell the difference so there's
a sort of equivalance principle
scale only ratios only ratios of lengths
are really important in physics only
ratios of di dimensional quantities so
what you can say is that the I mean I
think that that is a very good point and
we should talk about that uh the
distance between galaxies divided by the
length of a meter stick is
increasing and that's really all you can
say
yeah or equivalently the meter stick is
decreasing yeah uh and you take your
choice but it's uh it's standard I mean
it's a matter of convention but we like
to think that the param parameters of
atomic physics and molecular physics and
all these things which hold meter sticks
together is fixed we like to imagine
that the mass of the electron is fixed
and all these fundamental parameters are
fixed
numbers the speed of light all but but
in particular dimensional numbers I
would not like I can do it I can say the
radius of a proton uh decreases with
time as the instead of saying the
universe expands
it is a matter of taste more than
anything else and a matter of historical
preference a matter of historical uh uh
convention that we tend to think of the
microscopic Atomic uh distances as fixed
things and they of course determine what
is a meter stick incidentally why is a
meter stick a meter long well what is a
meter a meter is a distance from your
nose to your arm why is is it so big in
atomic units because it takes a lot of
atoms to make an
arm okay so it's a matter of
biology but that biology we like to
imagine doesn't change with time and so
we use conventions which say that the
size of an atom the size of a proton and
so forth uh is determined by a fixed set
of parameters that are enshrined in the
uh in somewh in Paris I don't know where
they keep the meter stick these days and
uh and finished we use those we use
those
units with that convention the universe
is
expanding if somebody big enough who
looks at the
universe from a large distance
perspective and likes to use the
distance between galaxies as a basic
unit that Observer will see everything
shrinking and shrinking we'll say atoms
get smaller so it it is a matter of
taste
uh and the question is is that the only
form of the metric that follows
from genus apart from apart from
coordinate Transformations now this is
the metric in some specific set of
coordinates in other words the right
statement is that the metric given these
two things the metric can be brought to
this form by an appropriate choice of
coordinates yeah yeah so that's a that's
in a sense a
derivation that I didn't do but uh but
it's it's not terribly hard yeah since
we were talking about running the tape
backwards if distance between two points
was Zero then the velocity would also be
zero which means there would not be no
I'm saying supposing no I'm saying
supposing we look at everything
today we calculate we measure what the
Hubble constant is
today okay today and then we run it
backward if we run it backward with
today's parameters that will tell us how
long it takes for the universe to
collapse into something much smaller the
Hubble constant of course varies with
time it varies with time uh and in fact
it tends to increase as you go back
toward the Big
Bang hoc constant was much larger at the
earlier times than it is today so um and
the velocities were much
larger
uh so even though the distance between
two galaxies may have been much smaller
the velocities of ejection of those same
galaxies was larger in the past that
means that the Hubble parameter must
have been much larger in the past okay
but what I'm saying is supposing we look
at things today we look at things
through our telescopes we measure
today's Hubble constant we know what it
is that tells us today what the ratio of
distance to Velocity is and then using
assuming that the velocity is uniform
and it doesn't change with time we can
ask how long it would have taken for a
collision
right then we add to that a little bit
of information from Gravity that as we
did if we did run it backward then we
would
be over under no overestimating the time
because the gravitational attraction
would cause things to speed
up
so uh and one can do this with great
Precision so we know what the age of the
universe the age of the universe meaning
the time until let's say galaxies would
have been sitting on top of each other
it's 13.5 billion
years let's uh let's uh proceed a little
bit how do we find out what a is doing
with time well one way of course is to
measure it and you can look back through
telescopes into the very very distant
past you can look at in principle you
can look at to galaxies you could in
principle try to in fact you don't do it
this way but you could look at them
carefully enough to see that they're
receding from each other a little bit
this was long long in the past and so in
that way you could measure the
relationship between their velocity and
their distance long in the past and uh
and determine how the Hubble parameter
changes with time and if you know that
you can also figure out how the scale
factor changes with time of course
that's not the way it's done the way
that it's actually done well is more
sophisticated than that but the first
thing is what should you expect what
should you expect on the basis of basic
Newtonian physics of uh of
gravity the answer is roughly analogous
to the same question that you would ask
about the
outgoing
Cannonball how does the distance of the
Cannonball remember what a is now a is
just the the distance between a pair of
uh nearby galaxies how does it vary with
time it varies with time in a manner
which is entirely analogous to the way
the bowling ball not the bowling ball
The Cannonball distance would recede
from the earth what governs that
Newton's equations governing forces and
acceleration determine how The
Cannonball would recede from the earth
and so the exercise of figuring out how
a varies with time is a simple exercise
in Newtonian physics in Newtonian fals
ma type physics and I'm going to show
you how it
works a simple
example let's uh draw all the galaxies
here they
are well it's not all of
them are in an approximation where the
universe is very big and the distance
between Galaxy is small and everything
is homogeneous and uniform we can think
of the galaxies sort of being
smeared over space in a very homogeneous
gas a sort of gas of
particles the gas of particles are more
or less standing still Rel they're not
standing still relative to each other
but they're flowing with the flow and
the gas of particles is
expanding let's say this is us over here
now there's no reason why we should be
concentrating on us and we'll discover
in the end that the equations don't
depend on who us is whether it's us over
here or somebody uh 5 billion light
years away the equations for How the
Universe expands should not depend on
who we choose to be us but let's choose
us anyway here's us over
here and now let's take some
Galaxy at point x let let's put it on
the x-axis let's put it on the x-axis we
are at xals Z by
definition here's a Galaxy at point x x
is its label its distance is a *
X so its distance the distance here the
actual distance in meters is a *
X here we are over here and let's solve
Newton's equations for how this galaxy
moves what are the forces on the Galaxy
on this galaxy this red Galaxy over here
well there is of course the force of
attraction to our galaxy but that's not
all there's a lot of other galaxies
here in between this is
forming a gas all of these galaxies and
there's also galaxies way out
here
all of these
galaxies gravitationally attract the
Galaxy that I've called X okay so it
sounds like a very very hard problem to
calculate the motion of X but Newton
would not have found it a hard problem
he I don't know I don't think he set up
this exact problem but he would not have
found it hard he would have used a fact
that he discovered about gravitational
forces it's basically a fact about
inverse Square forces here's the
statement if you have a spherically
symmetric distribution of
matter spherically symmetric about the
origin here and the uniform distribution
of galaxies is spherically symmetric
means it's the same in every
direction then the net
force on an
object is the force due to all of the
matter inside the sphere about the
center in other words the net force
pulling this galaxy toward the center of
coordinates us is due to all of the
matter inside the sphere and all of the
matter outside the sphere doesn't
contribute
anything that's one
statement so in calculating how X moves
you can forget all all the material on
the
outside just doesn't make any
difference on the other hand Newton also
discovered something else he discovered
that if you have a spherically symmetric
distribution of mass like this then the
force on an object due to the
spherically symmetric Mass Distribution
on the inside of the sphere is exactly
the same as if all the mass were
concentrated right at the
center so this means all we have to do
to find out how a Galaxy at distance X
moves how it moves is to study its
motion in a fictitious
problem where all of the material within
a
sphere bounded by X all the things
closer than x are all concentrated right
at
us and then just pretend it was a
problem in which a cannonball was
ejected from
uh from the earth and that will give us
the exact correct answer that's the
that's the thing that Newton would have
known and I'm sure if he didn't solve
that problem he would have solved that
problem very easily so let's work it out
well I don't know maybe we should quit
now I think we'll work it out next time
we'll work out in detail the equation of
motion for how a increases with time and
work out the simplest cosmology what's
called matter dominated cosmology find
out how a
increases and
uh
um discover one of
the basic laws of cosmology that uh that
we'll talk about next time are there
questions now because uh we'll do one
more class we'll finish this up and
that'll be it for the
summer no questions yeah um probably too
much to answer in a couple minutes I let
me at least ask
we look way out into the universe and we
see
like 123 billion years ago but 12 or 13
billion years ago the universe was very
small so why aren't we seeing that very
close to us instead
of
um the universe things were much closer
to us it's this it's this um equation
for the light R here
let's see um what are you asking
me
the the light that we
see I'm not sure how to how to describe
this say it again second part of the
question we look way out un and we see
12 13 billion years ago okay and it's
it's been coming at us for 12 13 billion
years no it's it's been it's been coming
at us for 12 or 13 billion years now but
12 or 13 billion years ago the universe
is much smaller so how can this light
appear to be from so far away well okay
so we have to work out how a light Ray
moves I'll do that next time I'm tired
now I'm reaching my exhaustion Point
let's work out next time exactly how
that works maybe the same question but
Ober Universe if if we the universe
started from a big bag and expanded in
the early days it was expanding much
slower than the speed of light how is it
that anything in the universe is not
observable to us it was all very Compact
and not
expanding okay so let's yeah uh it is
the same question um
let's let's plot some light rays here's
t
here's
X
okay now what happens to the scale
factor very early in time is that it
gets very small in fact let's just
assume it goes to zero in some simple
way okay um and let's plot what a light
Ray looks like when a is very very
[Music]
small uh the DX by D d t is very very
large so the light Ray let's say the
light Ray starting from this point over
here this is t equal
0 and at T equals z a is also very very
small essentially zero okay so the light
Ray starts out very fast measured in
X because a is very small and if a is
small then the distance that it goes in
a given interval of time is very large
so it starts moving very fast let's see
that means fast means almost
horizontal an infinite speed would mean
completely horizontal right then as a
starts to
grow
the co I'll call this the coordinate
velocity it's not the ordinary velocity
but the coordinate velocity of the light
begins to slow down and the light uh
light slows down According to some law
that depends on how a varies with
time okay now here we are right over
here here we are and here's
today space is flat goes on and on
forever and
ever no matter what this curve is shaped
like if we displace it over to here and
run it backward we will come to some
point point we'll come to some point
that's the point which sends light to us
from tal 0 that gets to us now that's it
the light that we see came from this
point there's uh I'm not I don't know
what else to say about it except that we
run this curve backward remember it it's
apparently slowing down slowing down
slowing
down and so wherever we start we can run
it backward and it will eventually
intersect tal 0 and I don't know what
else to say I mean it uh except to work
out some examples of uh of how light
propagates so there will be some
place that uh that the light originated
at if you we'll work out we'll work out
an example with a specific AF of and
we'll try to calculate how far
away that light originated
from and how long it took to get to us
I'm running out of steam so I don't want
to try to do it now but uh we can do
it um so when this big bang event
happens and how come I guess matter
didn't all
expand at the same like rate so that
everything should be organized in like a
ring no it didn't blow up from a
point everything started out completely
homogeneous as started out completely
uniform but extremely dense the tabletop
here went on and on forever now that's
probably not really true but just
imagine it the tabletop is extremely big
but extremely
dense so that uh so that molecules that
or molecules let's think of them as
molecules but molecules that we see
today is being uh 10 billion light years
away from us are really uh 10 Theus 10th
CM uh close to us everything that's in
today's observable universe today's
observable universe was all in a tiny
tiny patch
here okay and then the whole the whole
tabletop started to
expand okay no shell there's no shell
that formed there's no sense in which
some matter was ejected from a point and
then went out and formed a shell just
everything started to uniformly
expand and so it continued to form a
completely homogeneous um space but the
separation between points just got
bigger and bigger think of a balloon
think of a balloon
expanding uh you start with a balloon
balloon is small and it's got a lot of
dots in it and then it expands the same
dots are further
apart but the balloon is uniformly
filled with dots it's not that if this
is our DOT over here we see dots on some
shell far away the entire balloon is
uniformly filled that's the nature of
the geometry we're talking about
homogeneous everywhere the same but
uniformly expanded so there's not
there's no assumption in that that the
universe is finite at that time no so I
mean
well Point blowing up it's not
necessarily a point blowing up you have
infinite expans you could have infinite
expanse at that point at that time that
all all goes boom but some things were
not not that but some things were not
affected because the fact that you
you're keeping that you can actually
measure the fact that you know you can
see that there's this scale factor and
things increasing means you're you're
assuming that your ruler isn't changing
yes because obviously there's something
that's that's
not varying or varying at the same rate
um as the as the expansion of the
universe
that how come the gravitational
attraction that
Force wasn't affected by this expansion
event oh I guess that's just the
way why the force wasn't well the for
the force
force from the force between a Galaxy
and our galaxy is affected by the
expansion the closer it is the stronger
the force but we want to work out the
consequences of that when this sphere
was much
smaller remember now only the things
within the sphere affect the motion of
this x relative to
us okay when all of this was much
smaller so that that same galaxy was
right over here there was a much larger
force on it but you would consider
gravity or the other forces to actually
have the same uh
strength during when it was everything
was closer together Universal
gravitational constant did not change
over time you the con the gravitational
constant did not change but the distance
between between us and other things did
change and so the force uh depends on
constant and also this
is a un is
expansion what say it again the
expansion the universe
expanding in cature do the cature is
expanding or is it just flat okay the
the observational evidence okay let's
let's begin with the Earth is the earth
curved or is the earth flat right if you
go out on a large plane uh you know the
schoolyard and you try to look around
you can't tell if the Earth is curved or
flat why because you're not sampling a
large enough portion of it to
tell yeah yeah that's right your
triangles will not be able you will not
be able to tell the only way you can
tell is to sample a large enough portion
of the earth so that you can actually
see its
curvature uh the same is true with the
universe if you only only get to sample
a portion small by comparison with the
radius of curvature the operating term
here is the radius of curvature and for
the Earth the radius of curvature is
just its radius unless you can sample a
part of the earth that's comparable to
the radius of the Earth you will not see
that it's uh that it's it's curved
particularly if you're a little bug
moving around on the surface of the
Earth okay you have to explore a region
which is more or less of some finite
fraction of the entire radius of the uh
Earth in order to observe the fact that
it's
curved um the same is true of the
universe you have to explore a portion
of the universe which is comparable not
necessarily comparable to but at least
some reasonably reasonably large
fraction of the radius of
curvature of space space is also may
also be curved if you explore two
smaller fr fraction of it you can't
detect the curvature all right so the
statement is
today what you might be able to do for
example is you could put and come back
to the Earth you might be able to put
limits on how big the Earth is by
exploring some triangles and uh you know
out on the football field assuming the
football field was nice and
flat uh you could put some bounds on how
big the Earth is you could uh by
measuring the angles of triangles and so
forth you would find that it's very
close to being flat and you would say
well the deviation from 180° is less
than
001 radians and therefore the Earth has
to be bigger than a certain size okay
otherwise you would have seen the uh the
funniness of
triangles same thing you can do by
exploring a region of space of size
billions of years measure triangles
various as astronomical ways measure
very very large triangles compute the
Angles and so forth and ask whether on
the scale that you're measuring there's
any visible
curvature the answer is no on the scale
that we've measured up till now we
cannot detect the presence of curvature
of the universe it appears to be
flat on a scale of 10 20 billion light
years the meaning of that is the same it
is for the Earth it means that if the
universe is curved its radius of
curvature is much bigger than the
visible
portion uh how much is much bigger 10
times bigger at least at minimum maybe
much more than that but at Absolute
minimum the universe is 10 times larger
in radius than the portion that we can
see and so that means that we can't
really detect the curvature very easily
is it really curved it might be now what
happens if it is curved it starts out
very curved so the curvature is large of
its curved a small sphere is highly
curved as the sphere expands the
curvature gets smaller and smaller until
when the sphere is as big as the Earth
we can barely see the
curvature so the numerical measure of
curvature on the surface of the
Earth uh decreases as the Earth gets
bigger and bigger the same thing is true
with the universe the curvature of the
universe decreases as the universe
expands and apparently the universe has
expanded so much that even if it were a
curved ball to begin with it's expanded
to the point where we can no longer
detect its
curvature the reason I asked you that
question is if it has
curvature and curvature should have two
components one is expanding the other is
Contracting right by its Nature by it
genitive nature so the UN in the
meantime must be contracted sorry
expanding the universe is known to be
expanding expanding yeah but if it has
curvature then there is a component to
it that's that's Contracting also Al no
no I mean the the the
um the expansion or contraction of the
universe is controlled by this AF
the universe could be flat it could be
positively curved it could be negatively
curved whether it's expanding or
Contracting is not determined by that
it's determined by how AF evolves if AF
continues to grow it's expanding if it
grows and Rec contracts then it Rec
contracts after a while if it's
Contracting then the universe is
shrinking
um there is a connection which is is no
longer apparently believed to be
true but there was an old connection
between the curvature of the universe
and whether it's going to recollapse
again uh that has changed and I will
tell you about it next time but um I
don't know expanding is expanding
Contracting is Contracting I wouldn't
say there's a component which is
Contracting and that's that's not the
way I think about it I don't know how to
think about it so that expansion and
cont contaction
coexist contraction could follow
expansion in the same way that a ball
thrown into the air which is receding
could fall back
down that's essentially the question is
this particle here moving away fast
enough that all of the mass within this
sphere is insufficient to pull it back
down in which case it will escape or or
is it moving slow enough so that the
mass within here will pull it back down
in which case the universe will
crash okay or uh or is it just in
between on the knife edge it appears to
be just in between on the knife edge
between uh basically right at the escape
Velocity okay let's
[Music]
uh the preceding program is copyrighted
by Stanford University please visit us
at stanford.edu